So over the long course of human history,
على امتداد تاريخ البشرية الطويل
the infectious disease that's killed more humans
لم يودِ أيّ مرضٍ معدٍ بحياة الناس
than any other is malaria.
بقدر الملاريا
It's carried in the bites of infected mosquitos,
تنتقل الملاريا عبر عضّات البعوض المصاب
and it's probably our oldest scourge.
وتعدّ أقدم جائحةٍ تحلّ بالبشرية
We may have had malaria since we evolved from the apes.
فربّما حملناها منذ تطورّنا من القردة
And to this day, malaria takes a huge toll on our species.
وإلى يومنا هذا، تزهق الملاريا أرواح الكثيرين منّا
We've got 300 million cases a year
حيث تتسبب بـ 300 مليون إصابةٍ كل عام
and over half a million deaths.
وما يزيد عن 500 ألف حالة وفاة
Now this really makes no sense.
ولكنّ هذا منافٍ للمنطق
We've known how to cure malaria
فقد نجحنا في شفاء مرضى الملاريا
since the 1600s.
منذ القرن السابع عشر
That's when Jesuit missionaries in Peru
عندما اكتشف المرسلون اليسوعيون في البيرو
discovered the bark of the cinchona tree,
لحاء شجرة الكينا
and inside that bark was quinine,
وعثروا داخل اللحاء على مادة الكينين
still an effective cure for malaria to this day.
التي تُستعمل إلى يومنا هذا في شفاء الملاريا
So we've known how to cure malaria for centuries.
فقد توصلنا إذًا إلى شفاء مرضى الملاريا منذ قرون
We've known how to prevent malaria since 1897.
وإلى الوقاية من المرض منذ عام 1897
That's when the British army surgeon Ronald Ross
عندما اكتشف طبيبٌ في الجيش البريطاني يدعى رونالد روس
discovered that it was mosquitos that carried malaria,
أنّ عدوى الملاريا تنتقل بواسطة البعوض
not bad air or miasmas, as was previously thought.
وليس عبر الهواء الفاسد أو بخار المستنقعات، كما ساد الاعتقاد
So malaria should be a relatively simple disease to solve,
ولهذا من المفترض ألّا نواجه صعوبةً في حلّ مشكلة الملاريا
and yet to this day, hundreds of thousands of people
ولكن، إلى يومنا هذا، لا يزال مئات الآلاف من الأشخاص
are going to die from the bite of a mosquito.
يموتون من جراء عضّة بعوضة
Why is that?
فما السبب؟
This is a question that's
قضّ هذا السؤال مضجعي
personally intrigued me for a long time.
فترةً طويلةً من الزمن
I grew up as the daughter of Indian immigrants
أنا ابنة مهاجرين هنود
visiting my cousins in India every summer,
اعتدت زيارة أقاربي في الهند خلال الصيف
and because I had no immunity to the local malarias,
ونتيجةً لعجز جهاز مناعتي عن مقاومة الملاريا المحلية
I was made to sleep under this hot, sweaty mosquito net every night
اضطررت للنوم في ظلّ ناموسيةٍ وأنا أقاسي الحرّ والعرق
while my cousins, they were allowed to sleep
بينما تنعّم أبناء عمومي بالنوم
out on the terrace and have
على الشرفة
this nice, cool night breeze wafting over them.
والتمتّع ببرودة نسيم الليل المنعش
And I really hated the mosquitos for that.
ولذلك كرهت البعوض
But at the same time, I come from a Jain family,
ولكنّ عائلتي تتبع الديانة الجاينية
and Jainism is a religion that espouses
والجاينية ديانةٌ
a very extreme form of nonviolence.
تطبّق مبدأ اللاعنف بصرامة
So Jains are not supposed to eat meat.
فلا يجوز لأتباعها تناول اللحوم
We're not supposed to walk on grass,
أو السير على العشب
because you could, you know,
لأنّكم، كما تعرفون،
inadvertently kill some insects when you walk on grass.
قد تقتلون الحشرات من دون قصد
We're certainly not supposed to swat mosquitos.
ولا يجوز لنا بتاتًا قتل البعوض
So the fearsome power of this little insect
ولهذا اتضحت لي قوة هذه الحشرة الصغيرة
was apparent to me from a very young age,
منذ سنٍّ مبكرة
and it's one reason why I spent five years as a journalist
ولذلك أمضيت خمس سنواتٍ أثناء عملي كصحافية
trying to understand, why has malaria
أبحث عن السبب الذي جعل من الملاريا
been such a horrible scourge for all of us for so very long?
ذلك الوباء العظيم الذي لازمنا منذ فترةٍ طويلة
And I think there's three main reasons why.
وأنا أعتقد أنّ ذلك يعود إلى ثلاثة أسباب
Those three reasons add up to the fourth reason,
وهي تفضي بنا إلى سببٍ رابع
which is probably the biggest reason of all.
يُعتبر على الأرجح أهمّها
The first reason is certainly scientific.
وأمّا السبب الأول فهو علميٌّ بالتأكيد
This little parasite that causes malaria,
فهذا الطفيلي الصغير الذي يسبب الملاريا
it's probably one of the most complex
يُعتبر أحد أكثر الكائنات الممرضة تعقيدًا
and wily pathogens known to humankind.
ومكرًا في تاريخ البشرية
It lives half its life inside the cold-blooded mosquito
فهو يعيش نصف حياته داخل جسم البعوضة ذات الدم البارد
and half its life inside the warm-blooded human.
والنصف الآخر داخل جسم الإنسان ذي الدم الحامي
These two environments are totally different,
تختلف هاتان البيئتان اختلافًا كليًّا
but not only that, they're both utterly hostile.
ولكنّهما بيئتان عدائيتان بشكلٍ كبير
So the insect is continually trying to fight off the parasite,
ولذلك يحاول جسم البعوضة التخلّص من هذا الطفيلي
and so is the human body continually trying to fight it off.
وكذلك يفعل جسم الإنسان
This little creature survives under siege like that,
ولكنّ هذا الكائن الصغير يستمر في الحياة تحت هذا الحصار
but not only does it survive, it has thrived.
لا بل يتكاثر وينتشر
It has spread. It has more ways to evade attack than we know.
إنّه يتمتّع بأساليب كثيرة لتجنّب الهجوم
It's a shape-shifter, for one thing.
فهو يقوم بتغيير شكله
Just as a caterpillar turns into a butterfly,
فكما يتحول اليسروع إلى فراشة
the malaria parasite transforms itself like that
كذلك يتحوّل طفيلي الملاريا
seven times in its life cycle.
سبع مراتٍ خلال دورة حياته
And each of those life stages not only looks totally different from each other,
ويختلف كلّ طورٍ من هذه الأطوار عن غيره
they have totally different physiology.
في الشكل وفي التركيبة الفيزيولوجية
So say you came up with some great drug
فإذا ما توصلنا إلى عقار ناجحٍ
that worked against one stage of the parasite's life cycle.
يقاوم طورًا من هذه الأطوار
It might do nothing at all to any of the other stages.
قد يعجز هذا العقار عن مقاومة الأطوار الأخرى
It can hide in our bodies, undetected,
وقد يختبئ الطفيلي في جسم الإنسان من دون اكتشافه
unbeknownst to us, for days, for weeks,
ومن دون علمنا لأيامٍ أو أسابيع
for months, for years, in some cases even decades.
أو شهورٍ أو سنواتٍ أو حتى لعقود
So the parasite is a very big scientific challenge to tackle,
فالطفيلي يمثّل تحديًا علميًّا جسيمًا
but so is the mosquito that carries the parasite.
وكذلك البعوضة الناقلة للمرض
Only about 12 species of mosquitos
تنتقل معظم أمراض الملاريا حول العالم
carry most of the world's malaria,
عبر 12 نوعًا من البعوض فقط
and we know quite a bit about the kinds of
ونحن على إطلاعٍ بأنواع الموائل المائية
watery habitats that they specialize in.
التي تسكنها هذه الأنواع
So you might think, then, well, why don't we just
ولذلك قد تقترحون
avoid the places where the killer mosquitos live? Right?
تجنّب الأماكن التي تتواجد فيها هذه الأنواع
We could avoid the places where the killer grizzly bears live
فبإمكاننا مثلًا تجنّب موائل الدببة القاتلة
and we avoid the places where the killer crocodiles live.
وكذلك موائل التماسيح القاتلة
But say you live in the tropics
ولكن لنفترض أنّكم تعيشون في منطقة استوائية
and you walk outside your hut one day
وفي أحد الأيام، خرجتم من الكوخ
and you leave some footprints in the soft dirt
وتركتم آثار أقدامٍ في الوحل
around your home.
المحيط بالمنزل
Or say your cow does, or say your pig does,
أو ربما قامت بذلك إحدى الأبقار أو الخنازير
and then, say, it rains,
ولنفترض أنّ الأمطار تساقطت بعد ذلك
and that footprint fills up with a little bit of water.
وامتلأت الحفرة التي خلّفتها أقدامكم بالمياه
That's it. You've created the perfect
عندها، يكون قد تشكّل بجانب المنزل
malarial mosquito habitat that's right outside your door.
الموئل الأنسب للبعوض الناقل للملاريا
So it's not easy for us to extricate ourselves from these insects.
ولذلك ليس من السهل تجنّب هذه الحشرات
We kind of create places that they love to live
فنحن نساهم في تشكيل موائلها
just by living our own lives.
خلال حياتنا اليومية
So there's a huge scientific challenge,
فهو تحديٌ علميٌّ كبير
but there's a huge economic challenge too.
وتحديٌ اقتصاديٌّ كذلك
Malaria occurs in some of the poorest
تنتشر الملاريا في أكثر المناطق فقرًا
and most remote places on Earth,
ونأيًا على وجه البسيطة
and there's a reason for that.
ويعود ذلك إلى سببٍ معيّن
If you're poor, you're more likely to get malaria.
فالفقراء معرّضون للإصابة بالملاريا أكثر من غيرهم
If you're poor, you're more likely to live
فهم يعيشون غالبًا في مساكن بدائية
in rudimentary housing on marginal land that's poorly drained.
ضمن أراضٍ هامشية، لا تتمتع بنظام تصريفٍ مناسب
These are places where mosquitos breed.
وفي هذه المناطق، يتكاثر البعوض
You're less likely to have door screens or window screens.
وغالبًا ما تفتقر هذه المساكن إلى شباكٍ توضع على الأبواب أو النوافذ
You're less likely to have electricity
وتعاني نقصًا في الكهرباء
and all the indoor activities that electricity makes possible,
وبالتالي يقلّ عدد الأنشطة المنزلية لحاجتها للكهرباء
so you're outside more.
ويبقى الناس خارجًا
You're getting bitten by mosquitos more.
ويزداد احتمال تعرّضهم لعضّات البعوض
So poverty causes malaria,
فالفقر يسبب الملاريا
but what we also know now is that malaria itself
ولكننا ندرك اليوم كذلك
causes poverty.
أنّ الملاريا تسبب الفقر
For one thing, it strikes hardest during harvest season,
فهي تنتشر مثلًا خلال موسم الحصاد
so exactly when farmers need to be out in the fields
وعوضًا عن الخروج إلى الحقول لجمع المحاصيل
collecting their crops, they're home sick with a fever.
يُضطر الفلاحون إلى ملازمة الفراش نتيجة الحمّى
But it also predisposes people to death
كما تزيد الملاريا من خطر الموت
from all other causes.
إذا تزامنت مع أسباب الموت الأخرى
So this has happened historically.
فعبر التاريخ
We've been able to take malaria out of a society.
تمكنا من تخليص مجتمعٍ ما من الملاريا
Everything else stays the same,
بينما بقي كلّ شيءٍ آخر على حاله
so we still have bad food, bad water, bad sanitation,
كالتغذية السيئة والمياه غير النظيفة والمرافق الصحية غير المناسبة
all the things that make people sick.
أيّ كلّ العوامل المسببة للأمراض
But just if you take malaria out,
ولكن بمجرّد التخلص من الملاريا
deaths from everything else go down.
انخفض معدّل الوفيات العائدة إلى الأسباب الأخرى
And the economist Jeff Sachs has actually quantified
ويوضّح عالم الاقتصاد جيف ساكس بالأرقام
what this means for a society.
تأثير الملاريا على المجتمع
What it means is, if you have malaria in your society,
فإذا عانى أحد المجتمعات الملاريا
your economic growth is depressed
ينخفض النمو الاقتصادي
by 1.3 percent every year,
بنسبة 1.3 في المائة
year after year after year, just this one disease alone.
كلّ سنة نتيجة هذا المرض لوحده
So this poses a huge economic challenge,
وهو ما يشكّل تحديًا اقتصاديًّا كبيرًا
because say you do come up with your great drug
فحتى لو توصلت إلى عقارٍ فعّال
or your great vaccine -- how do you deliver it
أو لقاحٍ ناجع
in a place where there's no roads,
كيف ستوزّعه في مكانٍ يفتقر لشبكة طرقية
there's no infrastructure,
وبنيةٍ تحتيّة
there's no electricity for refrigeration to keep things cold,
وكهرباء لتبريد اللقاح وحفظه
there's no clinics, there's no clinicians
وعياداتٍ وطاقمٍ يعمل فيها
to deliver these things where they're needed?
ويقوم بتوزيع هذه اللقاحات
So there's a huge economic challenge in taming malaria.
فالسيطرة على الملاريا تمثّل تحديًا اقتصاديًّا مهولًا
But along with the scientific challenge and the economic challenge,
وبالإضافة إلى التحدي العلميّ والاقتصادي
there's also a cultural challenge,
تشكّل الملاريا تحديًا ثقافيًّا
and this is probably the part about malaria
وهذا هو الجانب
that people don't like to talk about.
الذي يتجنب الناس الحديث عنه
And it's the paradox that the people
وتكمن المفارقة في التناسب العكسي
who have the most malaria in the world
بين مدى انتشار الملاريا في مجتمعٍ ما
tend to care about it the least.
ومدى اهتمام هذا المجتمع بالمرض
This has been the finding of medical anthropologists again and again.
وهي النتيجة التي بلغها علماء الطبّ البشري
They ask people in malarious parts of the world,
فعندما سألوا الناس في المناطق المتأثرة بالملاريا
"What do you think about malaria?"
عن موقفهم من هذا المرض
And they don't say, "It's a killer disease. We're scared of it."
لم يتحدث أولئك عن الملاريا كمرضٍ مميتٍ ومخيف
They say, "Malaria is a normal problem of life."
بل اعتبروها مشكلةً حياتية عادية
And that was certainly my personal experience.
وقد لمست الموقف ذاته شخصيًّا
When I told my relatives in India
فعندما أخبرتُ أقاربي في الهند
that I was writing a book about malaria,
أنني بصدد تأليف كتابٍ عن الملاريا
they kind of looked at me like
كنتُ في نظرهم
I told them I was writing a book about warts or something.
كمن يؤلف كتابًا عن الثآليل
Like, why would you write about something so boring,
فقد تساءلوا جميعهم عن سبب اختياري موضوعًا
so ordinary? You know?
مملًّا واعتياديًّا
And it's simple risk perception, really.
إنّ لهذا علاقة بنظرة كلّ فردٍ إلى المرض
A child in Malawi, for example,
فقد تصاب طفلةٌ في مالاوي مثلًا
she might have 12 episodes of malaria before the age of two,
12 مرةً بمرض الملاريا قبل بلوغها السنتين
but if she survives,
وفي حال نجاتها
she'll continue to get malaria throughout her life,
ستصاب بالملاريا من جديد خلال حياتها
but she's much less likely to die of it.
ولكنّ احتمال وفاتها سينخفض بشكلٍ كبير
And so in her lived experience,
فبناءً على تجربتها هذه
malaria is something that comes and goes.
تنظر إلى الملاريا كمرضٍ عارض
And that's actually true for most of the world's malaria.
وهو ما ينطبق على معظم أنواع الملاريا في العالم
Most of the world's malaria comes and goes on its own.
فهي تصيب الإنسان ثم تزول من جراء نفسها
It's just, there's so much malaria
ولكن نتيجة انتشار الملاريا على نطاقٍ واسع
that this tiny fraction of cases that end in death
تبلغ الحالات التي تنتهي بالموت
add up to this big, huge number.
معدلاتٍ ضخمة
So I think people in malarious parts of the world
ولذا أعتقد أنّ سكان المناطق المتأثرة بالملاريا
must think of malaria the way
ينظرون إلى المرض
those of us who live in the temperate world
كما ننظر نحن سكان المناطق المعتدلة
think of cold and flu. Right?
إلى الزكام والأنفلونزا
Cold and flu have a huge burden on our societies
فهما يشكلان عبئًا كبيرًا على مجتمعاتنا
and on our own lives,
وعلى حياتنا
but we don't really even take
ولكننا لا نتخذ أيّ تدابير
the most rudimentary precautions against it because
أولية للوقاية منهما
we consider it normal to get cold and flu
فنحن لا نستغرب الإصابة بالأنفلونزا
during cold and flu season.
خلال موسم الأنفلونزا
And so this poses a huge cultural challenge in taming malaria,
فكبح الملاريا إذًا يشكّل تحديًا ثقافيًّا
because if people think it's normal to have malaria,
فإذا اعتقد الناس أنّ الإصابة بالملاريا أمرًا اعتياديًّا
then how do you get them to run to the doctor
كيف نقنعهم بأن يهرعوا إلى الطبيب
to get diagnosed, to pick up their prescription,
لتلقي التشخيص والعلاج
to get it filled, to take the drugs,
وشراء الأدوية اللازمة
to put on the repellents, to tuck in the bed nets?
واستخدام طارد البعوض والناموسيات؟
This is a huge cultural challenge in taming this disease.
فالجانب الثقافي إذًا قد يعيق عملية القضاء على الملاريا
So take all that together.
والآن لنلخّص ما سبق
We've got a disease. It's scientifically complicated,
إننا نواجه مرضًا معقدًا من الناحية العلمية
it's economically challenging to deal with,
يعدّ التخلص منه تحديًا اقتصاديًّا
and it's one for which the people who stand
وأمّا أكثر من يعانون منه
to benefit the most care about it the least.
يولونه أقل اهتمامٍ ممكن
And that adds up to the biggest problem of all,
وهو ما يفضي إلى أهم مشكلةٍ نواجهها
which, of course, is the political problem.
وهي بالطبع المشكلة السياسية
How do you get a political leader to do anything
فكيف نقنع القادة السياسيين بالتحرك
about a problem like this?
لمواجهة هذا المرض؟
And the answer is, historically, you don't.
لقد أثبت لنا التاريخ استحالة ذلك
Most malarious societies throughout history
فمعظم المجتمعات التي تعاني الملاريا
have simply lived with the disease.
لطالما تعايشت مع هذا المرض
So the main attacks on malaria have come
وأما الحملات الرئيسية ضد المرض
from outside of malarious societies,
فكانت تأتي من خارج هذه المجتمعات
from people who aren't constrained
يقودها أناسٌ لا يخضعون
by these rather paralyzing politics.
لهذه القيود السياسية
But this, I think, introduces a whole host of other kinds of difficulties.
ولكنّ ذلك، باعتقادي، يأتي بصعوباتٍ أخرى
The first concerted attack against malaria
بدأت أولى الحملات المنسقة ضد الملاريا
started in the 1950s.
في خمسينيات القرن الماضي
It was the brainchild of the U.S. State Department.
بقيادة وزارة الخارجية الأميركية
And this effort well understood the economic challenge.
أدرك أصحاب الحملة التحدي الاقتصادي
They knew they had to focus on cheap, easy-to-use tools,
فاستعملوا أدواتٍ منخفضة الكلفة وسهلة الاستخدام
and they focused on DDT.
وخاصةً مبيد الحشرات دي دي تي
They understood the cultural challenge.
كما فهموا التحدي الثقافي
In fact, their rather patronizing view was that
فأدوا دور الأولياء
people at risk of malaria shouldn't be asked to do anything at all.
ولم يطلبوا من المعرّضين للملاريا المساهمة
Everything should be done to them and for them.
بل قرروا خدمتهم وتقديم المساعدة لهم
But they greatly underestimated the scientific challenge.
ولكنّهم قللوا من شأن التحدي العلميّ
They had so much faith in their tools
فوضعوا كامل ثقتهم في الوسائل المستخدمة
that they stopped doing malaria research.
وتوقفوا عن إجراء البحوث المتعلقة بالملاريا
And so when those tools started to fail,
وعندما بدأت هذه الوسائل تفشل في تحقيق المطلوب
and public opinion started to turn against those tools,
وتواجه معارضة الرأي العام
they had no scientific expertise to figure out what to do.
افتقر أصحاب الحملة للخبرات العلمية لإيجاد البديل
The whole campaign crashed, malaria resurged back,
فانهارت الحملة بكاملها وعادت الملاريا للظهور
but now it was even worse than before
بشكلٍ أسوأ من أيّ وقتٍ مضى
because it was corralled into the hardest-to-reach places
لأنّها تركزّت في المناطق التي يصعب الوصول إليها
in the most difficult-to-control forms.
واتخذت أشكالًا تصعب السيطرة عليها
One WHO official at the time actually called that whole campaign
واعتبر أحد مسؤولي منظمة الصحة العالمية الحملة حينها
"one of the greatest mistakes ever made in public health."
"أجسم الأخطاء التي ارتُكبت في تاريخ الصحة العامة"
The latest effort to tame malaria started in the late 1990s.
بدأت آخر جهود كبح الملاريا في التسعينيات
It's similarly directed and financed primarily
وهي تخضع لقيادةٍ وتمويلٍ
from outside of malarious societies.
من خارج المجتمعات المصابة
Now this effort well understands the scientific challenge.
يدرك أصحاب الحملة التحدي العلميّ
They are doing tons of malaria research.
ويجرون بحوثًا كثيرة في مجال الملاريا
And they understand the economic challenge too.
كما يعوون التحدي الاقتصادي
They're focusing on very cheap, very easy-to-use tools.
ويركزون على وسائل منخفضة الكلفة وسهلة الاستخدام
But now, I think, the dilemma is the cultural challenge.
ولكنّ المعضلة الحالية برأيي تتمثل بالتحدي الثقافي
The centerpiece of the current effort is the bed net.
تركّز الحملة على إشاعة استخدام الناموسية
It's treated with insecticides.
المعالجة بالمبيدات الحشرية
This thing has been distributed across the malarious world
وُزّعت هذه الناموسيات عبر المجتمعات المصابة
by the millions.
بالملايين
And when you think about the bed net,
ويشبه استخدام الناموسية
it's sort of a surgical intervention.
التدخل الجراحي
You know, it doesn't really have any value
فهي تؤدي دورًا وقائيًّا
to a family with malaria except that it helps prevent malaria.
وبالتالي لا تساعد العائلات المصابة بالملاريا
And yet we're asking people to use these nets every night.
ولكننا لا زلنا نطلب من الناس استعمالها كل ليلة
They have to sleep under them every night.
والنوم في ظلّها كل مساء
That's the only way they are effective.
فهي الطريقة الوحيدة للاستفادة منها
And they have to do that
وهم مضطرون للقيام بذلك
even if the net blocks the breeze,
حتى ولو قطعت هذه الناموسيات النسيم
even if they might have to get up in the middle of the night
وحتى لو اضطروا إلى النهوض في منتصف الليل
and relieve themselves,
لقضاء الحاجة
even if they might have to move all their furnishings
وحتى لو اضطروا إلى إعادة ترتيب الأثاث
to put this thing up,
لتركيب الناموسية
even if, you know, they might live in a round hut
وحتى لو كانوا يعيشون في كوخٍ دائري
in which it's difficult to string up a square net.
يصعب فيه تعليق ناموسيةٍ مربعة الشكل
Now that's no big deal if you're fighting a killer disease.
تقلّ أهمية هذه التغييرات في مواجهة مرضٍ مميت
I mean, these are minor inconveniences.
فهي تشكّل إزعاجًا بسيطًا
But that's not how people with malaria think of malaria.
ولكنّ للمصابين بالملاريا رأيًا آخر
So for them, the calculus must be quite different.
فهم يتمتعون بوجهة نظرٍ مغايرة
Imagine, for example, if a bunch of well-meaning Kenyans
تخيّلوا مثلًا أنّ كينيين حسنيّ النية
came up to those of us in the temperate world and said,
أتوا إلى سكان المناطق المعتدلة قائلين:
"You know, you people have a lot of cold and flu.
"إنّ أمراض الزكام والأنفلونزا منتشرة لديكم
We've designed this great, easy-to-use, cheap tool,
ولذلك صممنا أداةً سهلة الاستخدام ومنخفضة الكلفة
we're going to give it to you for free.
وسنقدمها لكم بالمجان
It's called a face mask,
وهي قناع
and all you need to do is
وكلّ ما عليكم فعله
wear it every day during cold and flu season
هو ارتداء هذا القناع يوميًّا خلال موسم الأنفلونزا
when you go to school and when you go to work."
عند ذهابكم إلى المدرسة والعمل"
Would we do that?
هل كنّا لنتبع هذه التعليمات؟
And I wonder if that's how people
ربما شابه هذا الموقف
in the malarious world thought of those nets
موقف سكان المناطق المصابة بالملاريا
when they first received them?
من الناموسيات عند استلامها
Indeed, we know from studies
وبالفعل، تشير الدراسات
that only 20 percent of the bed nets
إلى استعمال 20 في المائة فقط
that were first distributed were actually used.
من الناموسيات الموزعة في بداية الحملة
And even that's probably an overestimate,
وهي نسبة مبالغٌ فيها على الأرجح
because the same people who distributed the nets
فالأشخاص ذاتهم الذين وزعوا هذه الناموسيات
went back and asked the recipients,
عادوا والتقوا بالمستفيدين
"Oh, did you use that net I gave you?"
وسألوهم ما إذا كانوا قد استعملوا الناموسية
Which is like your Aunt Jane asking you,
كما هي الحال عندما تسألك العمة جاين
"Oh, did you use that vase I gave you for Christmas?"
إذا استعملت الإناء الذي أهدتك إياه في عيد الميلاد
So it's probably an overestimate.
فالنسبة على الأرجح لا تعكس الواقع
But that's not an insurmountable problem.
ولكنّها مشكلةٌ يمكن تجاوزها
We can do more education,
فبإمكاننا تعزيز حملات التوعية
we can try to convince these people to use the nets.
وإقناع الناس باستخدام الناموسية
And that's what happening now.
وهذا ما يحصل اليوم
We're throwing a lot more time and money
فنحن نصرف الكثير من الوقت والمال
into workshops and trainings and musicals and plays
في تنظيم ورشات العمل والتدريب والحفلات الموسيقية والمسرحيات
and school meetings,
والاجتماعات في المدارس
all these things to convince people
وذلك في محاولةٍ لإقناع الناس
to use the nets we gave you.
باستخدام الناموسيات التي نوزعها
And that might work.
وقد ننجح في مسعانا
But it takes time. It takes money.
ولكنّ ذلك يتطلب مزيدًا من الوقت والمال
It takes resources. It takes infrastructure.
إضافةً إلى الموارد والبنية التحتية
It takes all the things that that cheap,
أي كلّ ما حاولنا تجنّبه
easy-to-use bed net was not supposed to be.
عبر استخدام الناموسية منخفضة الكلفة وسهلة الاستخدام
So it's difficult to attack malaria from inside malarious societies,
إنّ من الصعب مكافحة الملاريا من داخل المجتمعات المصابة
but it's equally tricky when we try to attack it
وكذلك الأمر عند مكافحتها
from outside of those societies.
من خارج هذه المجتمعات
We end up imposing our own priorities
فعندها نفرض الأولويات الخاصة بنا
on the people of the malarious world.
على سكان هذه المجتمعات
That's exactly what we did in the 1950s,
وهو ما حدث بالضبط في الخمسينيات
and that effort backfired.
فعاد عندها المسعى بنتائج عكسية
I would argue today,
وأنا أعتقد أنّ
when we are distributing tools that we've designed
توزيع هذه الأدوات التي صممناها
and that don't necessarily make sense in people's lives,
والتي لا تتماشى بالضرورة مع حياة الناس
we run the risk of making the same mistake again.
قد يقودنا إلى المصير ذاته
That's not to say that malaria is unconquerable,
لا أقصد القول إنّ القضاء على الملاريا مستحيل
because I think it is,
فأنا أؤمن بخلاف ذلك
but what if we attacked this disease
ولكن ماذا لو كافحنا هذا المرض
according to the priorities of the people who lived with it?
وفقًا لأولويات الناس المتعايشين معه؟
Take the example of England and the United States.
ففي انكلترا والولايات المتحدة مثلًا
We had malaria in those countries for hundreds of years,
عانينا الملاريا لمئات السنين
and we got rid of it completely,
وتخلصنا منها كليًّا
not because we attacked malaria. We didn't.
ليس عبر مكافحة الملاريا
We attacked bad roads and bad houses
بل عبر مكافحة الشبكات الطرقية والمساكن السيئة
and bad drainage and lack of electricity and rural poverty.
والصرف الصحي غير المناسب وغياب الكهرباء والفقر في الأرياف
We attacked the malarious way of life,
لقد كافحنا أسلوب الحياة الذي يسبب الملاريا
and by doing that, we slowly built malaria out.
فتخلصنا من الملاريا تدريجيًّا عن طريق التنمية
Now attacking the malarious way of life,
مكافحة أسلوب الحياة هذا هو الحل
this is something -- these are things people care about today.
فهذه هي الإصلاحات التي تسترعي انتباه الناس اليوم
And attacking the malarious way of life,
ولا يعدّ هذا الحل
it's not fast, it's not cheap, it's not easy,
سريعًا أو سهلًا أو منخفض الكلفة
but I think it's the only lasting way forward.
ولكنني أعتقد أنّه الحل المستدام الوحيد
Thank you so much.
شكرًا جزيلًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)